All right, today's דף daf *Daf* is דף ז' *Daf Zayin* and
we start at the top of the page, top of the דף
*Daf*. The discussion is the nature of טומאה Tuma בציבור b'tzibur, *Tuma
BeTzibur*. This is a classic question. טומאה הותרה בציבור Tuma hutra b'tzibur
*Tuma Hutra BeTzibur*, טומאה Tuma דחויה בציבור d'chuya b'tzibbur *Tuma Dechuya BeTzibur*.
Comes up multiple places but this is one of the central places.
Is טומאה tumah. *Tuma* permitted for קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibur, *Korban Tzibur*
or is it overridden? You know one way of thinking about this
is is it that when the Torah says don't bring a קרבן
Korban, בטומאה b'tuma. *Korban BeTuma*, is the Torah saying don't bring a
קרבן יחיד korban yachid בטומאה b'tuma? *Korban Yachid BeTuma* but by a
קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibur, *Korban Tzibur* it wasn't said? There was no
prohibition. You're not doing anything wrong. It's not a violation at all.
Or that's הותרה Hutra? *Hutra*, like there's no it's exactly what you're
supposed to be doing. There's not even a prohibition in this case.
Or is it טומאה tumah. דחויה Dechuya *Tuma Dechuya*? No, you actually
are violating but your mandate is to violate and therefore but the
violation is being overridden and because we are still recognizing it as
a violation
therefore obviously in an ideal world we'd like to not have the
violation and that would lead to certain choices to try to minimize
when you have to actually violate.
In a more immediately relevant question for us a similar issue gets
raised about פיקוח נפש *Pikuach Nefesh* on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* as I
mentioned at the end of yesterday. Is it when you have to
break שבת *Shabbos* to save a life, is it as I just
said you're breaking שבת *Shabbos* but your mandate to save a life
overrides, or is it that it's not considered breaking שבת *Shabbos* at
all, that's not חילול שבת *Chilul Shabbos*, that's what you're supposed to
do on שבת *Shabbos* to save a life regardless of what type
of activity it requires?
And you know part of that can be also a very big
question because if you think well I'm breaking שבת *Shabbos* but I'm
allowed to, you'll try to minimize your breaking of שבת *Shabbos* and
you might minimize your breaking of שבת *Shabbos* at the expense of
increasing the risk on somebody's life. So obviously that is an extremely
sensitive question and all the sort of literature around פיקוח נפש *Pikuach
Nefesh* on שבת *Shabbos* says you don't hesitate at all, you know
you don't make any חשבונות *Cheshbonos*, you just go, you save a
life and so on. And then of course there's an important asterisk
in parenthesis, of course if it's absolutely no more difficult than to
do it in a way that doesn't involve חילול שבת *Chilul Shabbos*,
of course you should do that. So you know you sort of
get like both messages but certainly the dominant message is don't hesitate,
do whatever you need to do. Anyway, that's the debate here and
it's
obviously connected to the idea of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen
Gadol* working on יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur* and not becoming
טמא Tamei. *Tamei* and how much we try to avoid him becoming
טמא Tamei. *Tamei* because if he were to be טמא Tamei, *Tamei*
you would do it anyway. There would only be one כהן Kohen
*Kohen* that could do it, again let's sort of bracket the idea
that you could have a substitute כהן Kohen, *Kohen*, but in theory
he could go ahead and do it anyway, so how much do
you have to actually work to avoid it if it is a
טומאה הותרה בציבור tumah hutrah betzibur *Tuma Hutra BeTzibur* or is it
טומאה tumah דחויה בציבור dechuya betzibur *Tuma Dechuya BeTzibur*? That is how
we enter the question and again one final point to also remind
us is that we're speaking specifically about טומאת מת *Tumas Meis* or
something like a טומאת מת *Tumas Meis*, which is something that's contact
from the outside as opposed to a טומאה tumah יוצא yotzei מגופו
*Tuma Yotzei MiGufo* which is for let's say the כהן Kohen, *Kohen*,
for a man it would be בעל קרי *Ba'al Keri*, a seminal
emission, or it would be having sex with a woman who had
been a נידה *Niddah*. That would not be about contact, that would
more be about transferring a personal status and that would not be
overridden. So those are things we clearly have to avoid, but the
question came around the טומאת מת *Tumas Meis*. Rabbi? Yes.
Is doing מלאכות *Melachot* on שבת *Shabbos* in the מקדש *Mikdash* go
into that category of הותרה hutra...
*Hutra* or דחויה dechuya, *Dechuya*? Right, so that's another question, you know
the fact that a קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibur. *Korban Tzibur* is brought
on שבת *Shabbat*, right? Is שבת נדחה *Shabbos Nidcheh* for the קרבן
ציבור Korban Tzibur. *Korban Tzibur*? It doesn't even apply. It's interesting that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't to the best of my knowledge, I
mean yes the פסוקים pesukim *Psukim* that tell you for example you
bring a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *Korban Pesach* on שבת *Shabbos* or
you bring a קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibur. *Korban Tzibur* on שבת *Shabbos*
is the same discussions in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and the same
derivations that you do with טומאה tumah, *Tuma*, but I do not
cannot on the top of my head recall a discussion about whether
the doing the קרבן Korban, *Korban* on שבת *Shabbos* is הותרה hutra
*Hutra* or דחויה Dechuya. *Dechuya*. There somehow seems to be an implicit
sense there that it's הותרה hutra *Hutra*. You know and there's a
lot of stuff you do for קרבנות Korbanot, *Korbanot*, you know
exactly
so that's a very good point in terms of that. So let's
take a look now at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, so that was
a debate between רב נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman* and רב ששת
Rav Sheshes, *Rav Sheshet*. רב נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman* says היתר
heter *Heter* and רב ששת Rav Sheshet, *Rav Sheshet* says דחויה d'chuya.
*Dechuya* and I'm going to pick up again you know two lines
from the bottom on ו' עמוד ב' *Vav Amud Beis* because that
gives us the more extreme formulation of their debate. איכא דאמרי *Ika
de'amrei*, others say, אפילו היכא דאיכא טהורים וטמאים בההוא בית אב *Afilu
heicha de'ika tehorim u'temeim be'hahu beis av*, when רב נחמן Rav Nachman.
*Rav Nachman* says הותרה Hutra *Hutra* he's saying even in an extreme
case, the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* that are working today, and we're not
talking about יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur* or anything, just a
normal day you have to bring the תמיד Tamid, *Tamid*, which is
a קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibur... *Korban Tzibur*, קרבן Korban *Korban* of the
fixed time, and there are טמא Tamei *Tamei* כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* and
טהור Tahor *Tahor* כהנים kohanim, *Kohanim* in today's shift, today's בית
אב *Beis av*, today's shift, פליגי *Pligi*,
רב נחמן Rav Nachman. *Rav Nachman*, רב נחמן Rav Nachman. *Rav Nachman*
would say okay so what? עבדי נמי טמאים tmeiyim? *Avdi nami temeim*,
look you're bringing a תמיד Tamid *Tamid*, go ahead, have the טמאים
Tmeim *temeim* do it. Why? You just ask the כהן Kohen *Kohen*
who's טהור Tahor *tahor* to do it? You don't have to, it's
a קרבן Korban תמיד Tamid *Korban Tamid*, it's
a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur *Korban Tzibur*. That's a real radical formulation.
permissible, there's not even a problem to at all, and that is
an extreme formulation of רב נחמן Rav Nachman as opposed to another
variation of him which would be, "No, if it's trivial you go
for that," but here the extreme is even if it's trivial there's
no need to opt for טהור Tahor over טמא. Tamei. Yes? So...
Okay, fine. So אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshes, "מנא מי לה?"
Mina mi-lah? So says רב ששת, Rav Sheshet. "Where do I get
my position from that we say דחויה d'chuya? and not הותרה?" hutrah,
דתניא, Desanya, we taught in the ברייתא, Braisa, "היה עומד ומקריב מנחת
העומר." Haya omed u-makriv minchas ha-omer. A כהן kohen was standing and
bringing the עומר Omer קרבן, Korban which is a מנחה, Mincha, right?
It's a flour and, you know, oil sacrifice, whatever, and he would
go ahead and whatever flour sacrifice, and he would go ahead and
he would bring it and put a קומץ, Kometz, a handbreadth up
on the altar. ונטמאת בידו. Ve-nitmeis b'yado.
And as he's bringing and as he's holding onto this קרבן, Korban
to this מנחה, Mincha, it becomes טמא. Tamei Who knows? A שרץ
Sheretz jumps into it. Okay. אומר, Omer,
אומר ומביא אחר תחתיה. omer u-meivi acher tachteiha. So he's there, he's
like up at the top of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. It's
funny the phrase אומר. omer.
So there's this interesting גרסא girsa on the side, I'll read in
a minute, but the way we have it, imagine he's up there
by the altar, he says, "Hey, I need a new עומר!" Omer!
Now that's עומר Omer with an ayin. He needs a new עומר
Omer or whatever. Anyway, so then they go ahead and they take
care of it and they bring. So he doesn't have to, I
guess, leave his post.
Did he say he's bringing another one?
What? Yeah, he says "Get me another one," and they bring him
another one.
I thought they only cut it once.
Apparently not. Apparently they had leftover flour. ואם אין שם אלא היא,
Ve-im ein sham ela hi, if this is the only available עומר
Omer to bring, this is the only flour they have to bring
and, whatever, it's not reasonable an option to get another one. אומרים
לו, Omrim lo, they say to him, "הוי פיקח ושתוק." Havei pikei'ach
u-shtok. Just, just do us a favor, just just keep it quiet,
keep it to yourself. Okay. So...
so that's very interesting. Why, I mean, if he's allowed to bring
it, then why does he have to be quiet about it? If
he's not allowed, how is he allowed to be quiet about it?
So anyway, but what you do see is, is that לכתחילה, l'chatchila,
here's a case of a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, the עומר, Omer,
it's קבוע זמן, kavo'a zman, it has to be brought today, and
it became טמא, Tamei. and you would prefer to get a טהור
Tahor one, not a טמא Tamei, one. So what's the answer? קתני
מיהא, Ketani m'ha, we taught nonetheless, you know the word מיהא m'ha
is interesting because מיהא m'ha signals the fact that we know that
there's like something a little bit, you know, weird about this, like
the fact that it's אומרים לו הוי פיקח ושתוק. omrim lo havei
pikei'ach u-shtok. But anyway, but the point we want to focus on
is that that... you would prefer that it become... to get a
טהור Tahor one, and you chase after a טהור Tahor one. So
קתני מיהא, Ketani m'ha, אומר ומביא אחר תחתיה. omer meivi acher tachteiha.
אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, "מודינא..." Modina... רב נחמן says, "I
would admit, היכא דאיכא שיריים לאכילה." heicha d'ika shyrayim l'achila. טומאה
הותרה בציבור tumah hutra betzibur, only allows you to bring the קרבן
Korban, בציבור, betzibur, to bring the קרבן Korban בטומאה. b'tuma It does
not allow you to eat it, with the one exception of... anybody?
What's the one קרבן Korban, that you can even eat בטומאה? b'tuma.
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach as we learned when we were dealing with
פסחים Pesachim because the point of bringing the קרבן פסח korban Pesach.
is not, is not the הקרבה, hakrava, but it's the אכילה. achila.
But every other קרבן Korban you bring it בטומאה b'tuma. you don't
eat it בטומאה. betumah? So he says, so therefore, if we're talking
about that we have an option of bringing a קרבן, Korban. it's
a קרבן Korban. that would be eaten, part of it would be
eaten, there I would say from the הקרבה hakrava perspective, no need
to prefer a טהור Tahor over a טמא. tamei But we are
going to in practice prefer טהור Tahor over טמא Tamei. because we
want it to be eaten. Not, we want it to be יוצא
yotzeh, the הקרבה hakrava of the קרבן, Korban? but we want it
to be eaten and not throw out the rest. And therefore we're
going to prefer a
טהור Tahor one, rather than a טמא. Tamei By the way, remember,
this is the קרבן Korban, that is טמא, Tamei, not the
כהן, kohen but it's
the
same sort of
same difference. I mean, at least for now it's the same difference.
I'll get back in a minute to discuss a way in which
it does matter. Yes? Okay, fine. What about the whole idea also
of people not walking around the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash while they're
טמאים? Because, you know, you're a כהן, maybe I'll do the דחויה,
duchuya I'm gonna go... Right. So
it's a good point. We should mention that there's the reason about
being טמא Tamei, in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash has nothing to
do with bringing a קרבן. Korban There's a sense about, you know,
entering into God's zone, to מחנה שכינה, Machaneh Shechinah, בטומאה. betumah? And
you'd have to do
that if you're going to do the קרבן. Korban.
Right, so that's a good question. How could there be כהנים טמאים
Kohanim Tmeiyim
bringing the קרבן? Korban, What are they doing, what are they doing
on, you know, in the עזרה? Azarah?
Could they be... Yeah, but would you say הותרה... hutrah, so it's
a... but but
but they הותרה hutrah only for... I wasn't thinking about that. Meaning,
it's not just the היתר הקרבה, heter hakrava, it's the היתר heter.
to be in the עזרה. Azarah. So what does it mean that
they're there in the עזרה? Azarah? You don't they only allowed to
go in even if from the הותרה hutrah perspective they'd only be
allowed to go in... when they're bringing the קרבן, Korban, you know,
when they're bringing the תמיד, Tamid which, so it's an interesting question
as as
that the
טומאה tumah is only permitted if most of the population, whatever that
population group is, is טמא.
Tamei. No, he doesn't seem to be saying that. He says you
have טמא Tamei and טהור tahor. and it's a קרבן ציבור, korban
tzibur there's no need to prefer one over the other. But I,
but it is a good question because it's one thing if they're
all standing around, but how are they even standing around? How did
the טמאי Tamei כהנים get עזרה Azara הר הבית? Har HaBayit? I'm
starting to think, is there any טומאה tumah. in the עזרה, Azara,
maybe look you could imagine that they would do the שחיטה Shechita
that they could be—no, you'd have to be the קרבן Korban doesn't
have—no. No. Improper שחיטה Shechita creates a נבילה. Neveila.
Yeah well the way
I understand, you had the lizard, the dead lizard fall into the
קרבן. Korban So how did the dead lizard fall—so
you could do that, that you're in the middle—you could say that,
you're in the middle of bringing the תמיד Tamid, and something, right,
I was thinking that that would be the scenario. You're in the
middle of bringing the תמיד tamid and somebody becomes טמא, Tamei. and
you don't say, hey buddy, stand down, let your friend take over.
What?
But we said before if הותרה hutra and we're saying that they're
עוסקים. Oskim.
Right. I know, but let's say they all start as טהור tahor.
and they're in the middle of doing the תמיד tamid? and one
becomes טמא, tamei, you don't say stand down, go get, you wait
for him to finish and then he leaves.
That's what you think?
I don't know, it's a very good question, I have to think
about that, that how do you, meaning you know, if we're talking
about you have no choice and you have to bring the קרבן,
korban so טמאים come in, fine. But if it's a scenario where
you had a choice, what let them, you know, walk on the
ground, but when they in the act of walking on the ground
they weren't yet bringing the תמיד, tamid? you know. So you have
to construct a scenario, I have to see if there's a discussion
about that, you have to construct the scenario.
Yeah though, we glossed over this humorously, but what do you mean
as הוי פיקח ושתוק? Hevei Pikeach Ve-Shtok?
We'll get to it, I haven't forgotten about it. Yeah, Charlie? And
then we'll go ahead, Charlie first.
But I must say, you screw up the שחיטה, Shechita, that creates
a נבילה, Neveila, you have to get rid of the נבילה Neveila
animals, so that's gonna get
people טמא.
tamei, That's true, that would be a scenario where it would happen
all of a sudden. Yes?
I want to know other examples where you don't have to confess
something, but just keep on going.
Oh okay, just keep on going. All right, so we'll get to—right,
right, so we'll get to that in a minute. I want to
just point out, so we are getting to that, I want to
point out by the way the marginal גרסא—I Girsa haven't forgotten, it's
just, it's coming up, okay? It's coming up. I want to point
out the marginal גרסא Girsa by the way, the גרסא Girsa in
the margin that says a slightly different version. Rather than אומר, Omer,
like he calls out for a קרבן, korban the סיפא Seifa speaks
again, אם יש שמה אחרת אומרים לו הרי. Im Yesh Shamma Acheret
Omrim Lo Harei. So it actually is a more nice parallel point,
which is the people around him, check it out, and if they
know that they have an extra one, they say here, here's a
substitute. And if they know they don't have an extra one, they
say just keep on going, just keep it quiet, keep on going.
So it's not that he calls out, but it's all about what
they're saying to him. Okay, so we'll get back to this question
about just keep it quiet. So let's take a look at one
more parallel case. מיתיבי, Meitivei, again says רב ששת, I'll ask you
an indication that we say דחויה. duchuya
היה מקריב מנחת פרים ואילים וכבשים—the Haya Makriv Minchat Parim Ve-Eilim U-Kevashim
כהן is bringing the מנחה, Mincha, the מנחת נסכים, Minchat Nesachim, the
flour, oil and wine that comes with
certain קרבנות, Korbanot, with עולות Olot and שלמים, Shelamim, and he is
bringing it for cows, rams, and sheep. Now what type of קרבן
korban. we'll see in a minute, but let's assume now it's a
קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur, ונטמאת בידו—and Ve-Nitmet Be-Yado the מנחת נסכים Minchat
Nesachim becomes טמא tamei, in his hand. Now the reason this is
going to be a better question is you do not do a
קומץ Komets for this מנחה, Mincha, everything gets burnt on the מזבח
Mizbeach for the מנחה Mincha that comes with the
קרבנות, korbanot the מנחת
נסכים. Minchat Nesachim. אומר ומביא אחרת תחתיה—he Omer U-Mevi Acheret Tachtei-ha lets
people know and he brings a substitute. Better bring a substitute than
something that's טמא. tamei, ואם אין שם אלא היא—if Ve-Im Ein Sham
Ela Hi there's no flour, imagine there's no other flour, oil and
wine to be found on the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but okay,
if there's some scenario that they cannot substitute it,
אומרים לו הוי פיקח ושתוק—just Omrim Lo Hevei Pikeach Ve-Shtok keep it
to yourself, keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara. says, so again
you see that he
is—that there's a preference
for it to be בטהרה Be-Tahara even though presumably this is something
that is
all burnt, there's no איסור Issur of eating it.
So מאי לאו פרים ואילים וכבשים דחג? Mai Lav Parim Ve-Eilim U-Kevashim
De-Chag? Wouldn't a good example for example be like a קרבן מוסף
Korban Musaf on סוכות? Sukkot? That has everything, that has one scenario
that has everything, it has cows, it has rams, it has sheep,
that's like the type of scenario we're talking about, and it's a
קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur אמר ליה רב נחמן—so Amar Lei Rav Nachman
רב נחמן will say back to you, ברקתי-הו, Barakti-hu, לא, Lo, no,
we're not talking about a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur פרים, Parim, the
case of cows or bulls I should say, or I don't know,
cows, bulls—is פר עבודה זרה, Par Avoda Zara,
is the bull that's bought for עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, which is
when the כל ישראל Klal Yisrael sins with the sin of עבודה
זרה, Avoda Zara, there's a special קרבן korban, that's brought that's a
cow, okay the bull, I say cow, a bull that is an
עולה. Olah. אף על גב דציבור הוא, Af Al Gav De-Tzibur Hu,
although it's a קרבן ציבור... korban tzibur Because it's for when the
entire כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael sins, כיון דלא קביע ליה זמן,
keivan delo kviya lei
zman,
it doesn't have a fixed time, מהדרינן, mahadrinan, we try to get
it בטהרה. betahara. Now this is the important point I pointed out
yesterday and I'll be repeating right now, which is that we often
talk about a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur is דוחה את הטומאה, docheh
et hatumah, but it's really not about a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur
it's really about fixed time קרבנות korbanot. that has to be done
now. You could have a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur, that is not
דוחה את הטומאה, docheh et hatumah, this is a great example. The
ציבור tzibur brings this bull for having done the sin of עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. It is a קרבן korban for the entire ציבור
tzibur but it could be brought at any time. It does not
override טומאה. tumah Here's an example of a קרבן יחיד korban yachid
that is קבוע לו זמן, kavua lo zman, קרבן korban, פסח. Pesach
Although everybody's bringing it, everybody's bringing it as individuals and therefore even
if you do call it a קרבן יחיד korban yachid and not
a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur. or here's a better example because the
גמרא Gemara says פסח Pesach, is like a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur
because it comes en masse. Here's a better example, Aaron's קרבן korban,
on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur Aaron the כהן גדול's kohen gadol קרבן.
korban It's a personal קרבן, korban it's not done for the sake
of the ציבור, tzibur, it may even come from his own funds,
right, we had that discussion in שקלים, Shekalim, but nevertheless, it has
to be done today. That does override טומאה. tumah Okay, so the
key for overriding טומאה tumah and overriding שבת is not as much
ציבור tzibur as it is fixed time. So his answer is, wait
a minute, we are not talking about a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur,
or not talking about something that overrides טומאה tumah that you say
הותרה, hutra we're talking about this thing that is yes a קרבן
ציבור korban tzibur but it doesn't have a fixed time. That would
be the פר par case. Let's read the whole thing and then
there's more to explain.
אילים elim the ram, באילו של אהרן, be'eilo shel Aaron, there you
go, Aaron's ram on יום כיפור, that is a, that is the
flip, that's a קרבן יחיד korban yachid, that has a fixed time.
דאף על גב דקביע ליה זמן, de'af al gav dekvi'a lei zman,
although it has a fixed time, כיון דיחיד הוא, keivan deyachid hu,
since it's a קרבן יחיד, korban yachid מהדרינן, mahadrinan, it's not a
קרבן ציבור korban tzibur, so in that case it doesn't have as
much of an override, we'd rather you get something טהור.
tahor We don't, we're not going to insist on it.
And כבשים, kvashim, and I'll get back to that in a minute,
כבשים kvashim in the case of the sheep, בכבשי דבאים עם העומר,
bekivsei d'ba'im im ha'omer, we're not talking, we're talking about the, not
so much about the
מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim, we're talking about
the sheep and the עומר omer that come together on the second
day of פסח, when you bring the עומר omer you bring a
קרבן korban. of sheep together with it, so we're not talking about
a מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim, we're really going back to talking about
the עומר omer like we were talking about before, which is a
stretch because a minute ago we were talking explicitly about the עומר,
omer, דאיכא שיריים לאכילה, de'ika sheyirayim le'achila, and there the reason we
want to prefer it is because so you can eat the remnant.
So basically, there's a lot to explain here, basically what the answer
is, here he says look you see that you prefer to do
it בטהרה, betahara, and the answer is no, the only reason you
prefer to do it בטהרה betahara is secondary issues. What are the
secondary issues? Number one is, we'll work reverse, what we said before,
scenario where you want to eat the remnant, like if it's the
עומר, omer, that's why we prefer to do it בטהרה. betahara. Or
in the other two cases, those are cases where yes it's טומאה
הותרה בציבור tumah hutra betzibur. but it's not an ideal case. It's
either a יחיד yachid which overrides because it's a fixed time or
ציבור tzibur which isn't a fixed time, it has one of the
normal two components and therefore since it's not the strongest case we
don't give it a total license, we don't say הותרה, hutra or
we don't give it the הותרה hutrah. with that degree of license,
we want to prefer you to use טהור. tahor Now, okay, conceptually
that all makes sense, there's only a problem which is is that
if you should come back to me and say Rabbi Lynch, I
understand the case with Aaron's קרבן, korban? it's a fixed time, it
has to be done, it overrides טומאה, tumah. so you want to
say it's on a slightly lower level because it's a קרבן korban,
יחיד yachid, not a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur so it doesn't have
as much of an override, we'll prefer טהרה, tahara, that I get.
Okay, we actually I mentioned that yesterday. It could be override, it
could be הותרה בציבור hutrah betzibur for a fixed time, but if
it's הותרה hutrah because it's fixed time but it's not בציבור, if
it's not a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, not a complete היתר. But
how about the ram for עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? That doesn't have
to be done today, so why are you doing it at all?
Right? Why should that at all be allowed to be done בטומאה?
betumah. I just got through telling you the whole idea that it
overrides טומאה tumah is because it has to be done today and
it's not fundamentally about it being a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur So
why does the ram, or not ram, why does the ox for
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, why is that allowed to be done בטומאה?
b'tumah, Right? What I was, one minute, so I don't want to
speculate, I'm unclear, is that clear what the question is? Right? If
you accept what I said that it's not about ציבור, tzibur, it's
about fixed time, what is this first answer? Now the first answer
explains why we prefer the טהור but this gets now back to
Dov's question and Risty's question, why if we can't get a טהור
do we say just keep it to yourself? At the end of
the day it is not a fixed time קרבן, korban you should
not be allowed to bring it בטומאה. b'tumah, Right? Good question. So
let's take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. Okay? תוספות Tosafot says like
this: פר פר דעבודה זרה. par par d'avodah zarah. פירוש: pirush: דעולה
הוא, de'olah hu, וטעון מנחת נסכים. veto'un minchat nesachim. אף על גב
דציבור הוא. af al gav detzibur hu. מדרינן *madrinan* והא דאמר *ve-ha
de-omer* אמר *omer* לו *lo* הוי פיקח ושתוק *hevi pikeach veshitok* ומביאתה
בטומאה betumah, *u-mevisah be-tumah* לאו משום דטומאה דחויה dechuyah, בציבור
*lav mishum de-tumah de-chuyah be-tzibur* דהלא *de-halo* דחי שבת *dachi shabbos* כיון
דלא קביע ליה זמן *keivan delo kevi leh zman*. So he says,
when we tell him if we can't find a substitute, oh just
keep it to yourself, it's not because fundamentally
a non-fixed time קרבן ציבור korban tzibur *korban tzibur* overrides טומאה tumah
*tumah*. No. If it's not a fixed time, it doesn't override טומאה
tumah? *tumah*. It doesn't override שבת *shabbos*, doesn't override טומאה tumah. *tumah*.
וטומאה נמי לא דחי *u-tumah nami lo dachi* כדאמרן לקמן *ked-amran le-kaman*
דכל שאינו זמן קבוע אינו דוחה לא את השבת ולא את הטומאה
*de-chol she-eino zman kavua eino docheh lo es ha-shabbos ve-lo es ha-tumah*.
That is the key line. It's not about it being a קרבן
ציבור korban tzibur. *korban tzibur*, it's about it being a fixed time.
So how do we say just keep it to yourself in this
case? אף על פי שקרבן ציבור tzibur? *af al pi she-korban tzibur*.
והא דמביא בטומאה היינו משום דריצוי ציץ tzitz *ve-ha de-mevia be-tumah hainu
mishum de-ritzui tzitz*. Okay so Michael, I'm sorry to take away your
thunder, but the reason that we have it בטומאה *be-tumah* is a
different principle, that there's an idea that the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* that
the כהן גדול kohen gadol *kohen gadol* wears, as the תורה Torah,
*torah* says, is מרצה mratzeh, *meratze* for the קרבנות korbanot, *korbanos* that
are brought בטומאה *be-tumah*. Okay, and that's the answer. So that is
how that functions. But תוספות Tosafot *tosafos* goes on to say that
only works when the קרבן korban *korban* itself is טמא tamei *tamei*.
It doesn't work when the person is טמא tamei, *tamei*. Okay, so
here then is the way that תוספות Tosafot *tosafos* understands that this
scenario works. You become טמא tamei, *tamei*. Okay, if you the person,
the כהן *kohen*, is טמא tamei, *tamei*, then the only way you
can be involved in bringing the קרבן korban *korban* is if it
is a fixed time קרבן korban *korban*. Then you need the overriding
that it has to be done today, the same way it overrides
שבת *shabbos*, it overrides טומאה tumah *tumah*. That's when you the person
is טמא tamei, *tamei* who's being involved in bringing the קרבן korban
*korban*. However, although you're trying to get another one in the case
of רב נחמן *rav nachman*, no, it doesn't have to be a
קרבן korban ציבור tzibur *korban tzibur*, like the אילו של אהרן *aylo
shel aharon*, which isn't a קרבן korban ציבור tzibur, *korban tzibur*. The
key principle is: fixed time. That's sufficient to override שבת *shabbos*, override
טומאה tumah. *tumah*. Then it allows even when the person is טמא
tamei, *tamei*. When the קרבן korban. *korban* is טמא tamei. *tamei*, we
will find out that there is always בדיעבד b'diavad *bedieved* that will
be good because of the ציץ tzitz *tzitz*. And therefore that allows
even though, forget טומאה tumah. *tumah* for a קרבן korban. ציבור tzibur
*korban tzibur*, forget a קרבן korban, ציבור tzibur *korban tzibur*, it's not
a קרבן korban ציבור tzibur *korban tzibur*, even if it was a
קרבן korban יחיד yachid, *korban yachid* and was brought and the קרבן
korban *korban* was טמא tamei. *tamei* but not the people, in that
case בדיעבד b'diavad *bedieved* it would be good because of the ציץ
tzitz. *tzitz*. And that's what this gets to the answer 'keep it
to yourself', which means we're not going to announce, make it obvious
we're bringing it בטומאה *be-tumah* because really you're not supposed to bring
it בטומאה *be-tumah*, especially this one that's not a fixed-time קרבן korban
*korban*. But when you do bring it בטומאה *be-tumah*, בדיעבד b'diavad? *bedieved*
it will be fine because we have the function of the ציץ
tzitz *tzitz* and most the remainder of today is a lot going
to be looking at the ציץ tzitz. *tzitz*. So just to just
to sort of clarify what we've got, okay, you have a fixed-time
קרבן korban *korban*, right? You have fixed time. And that you could
have one that's ציבור tzibur, *tzibur*, for example like תמיד tamid *tamid*,
מוסף *musaf*, you know, all those other things, יום כיפור *yom kippur*
for the people. And then you can have a fixed time which
is a יחיד yachid *yachid*, which is the כהן גדול kohen gadol
*kohen gadol*'s, you know, one of יום כיפור *yom kippur*, right, his
ram, and you have a case of פסח *pesach* which is somewhat
in between because פסח *pesach* is like a
pseudo-ציבור tzibur. *tzibur* because it's... oh that's an interesting a good example,
a good example, the עשירית האיפה *asiris ha-eiphah* of the כהן גדול
kohen gadol. *kohen gadol*. Okay, so two cases of the כהן גדול
*kohen gadol* which is a private one. Because it's fixed time, the
הלכה halacha, *halacha* is that it overrides שבת *shabbos* and it overrides
טומאה tumah *tumah*. That is the key; it has to be done
today. Now because this has the weakness of יחיד *yachid*, the גמרא
Gemara *gemara* is saying that even according to רב נחמן *rav nachman*
that says הותרה *huttra* and you don't necessarily prefer in a normal
case you wouldn't even have to give any preference to a טהור
*tahor* because of the weakness of יחיד *yachid*, although we say הותרה
*huttra* here according to רב נחמן *rav nachman*, here we say in
the case of the יחיד *yachid* we say try to be טהור
*tahor*. Okay, that's what we say. Okay, so that's basically a fixed
time, override טומאה tumah *tumah*, override שבת *shabbos*, according to רב נחמן
*rav nachman* it's הותרה *huttra*, you can even לכתחילה l'chatchila, *lechatchila* have
a טמא tamei *tamei* person in the extreme formulation, but if it
has the weakness of the יחיד *yachid*, then we say okay there
at least we'll try to be טהור *tahor*. That's why we're trying
to be טהור *tahor* in that case, in that other case. Then
you have non-fixed time, right? And you can have non-fixed time, which
is most קרבנות korbanot *korbanos*. You could have ציבור *tzibur*, which would
be like the פר *par* of עבודה זרה avodah zarah, *avodah zarah*
and the יחיד *yachid* which is pretty much
everything. And that doesn't override שבת *shabbos*, that does not override anything.
But, so how then when we're talking about פר *par* of עבודה
זרה avodah zarah, *avodah zarah* becoming טמא tamei, *tamei* we say 'just
keep it to yourself'? Because in this case if the קרבן korban
*korban* is טמא tamei, *tamei*, okay, if the כהן *kohen* is טמא
*tamei*, no override, invalid.
Usually we were using override in the case of דחויה *de-chuyah*, but
here you're talking about הותרה *huttra*.
Okay right, override or let's say permitted. All right, all right, I
wasn't being specific. Anyway,
if the קרבן korban is טמא, then we say there's a principle
of ריצוי ציץ. ritzuy tzitz. Okay, so this is basically I'm not
sure if I could have made that chart in a different way
that would have been clearer, but my point is that the idea
of טומאה הותרה tumah hutra or דחויה בציבור is about fixed time
קרבנות. korbanot Okay, and if it's a happens to be a יחיד,
maybe we won't go as extreme and totally say ignore טומאה. tumah
If it's non-fixed time, this concept does not apply, and so if
the person is טמא, it's it's no good, but if the קרבן
korban is טמא, like the גמרא'ס Gemara's case of the פר עבודה
זרה, par avodah zarah, then you could say all right, all right,
keep it to yourself and in the end it'll all be okay
anyway. All right, now the funny thing is, and Rifka this again
goes to your point of keep it to yourself, is that normally
when we say that the ציץ tzitz is מרצה, it's once בדיעבד
b'diavad it's brought, and here you're keeping it to yourself and going
ahead and bringing it even לכתחילה, l'chatchila okay, and that might be
because you already brought the קרבן itself and we want to finish
it up, you know, but that's an interesting quality to it. It's
right, right, but it but it is interesting in terms of that,
yes.
Also that בדיעבד b'diavad, there's no other opportunity to bring it.
Right, right, so that could be, right, how do you define sort
of בדיעבד? b'diavad בדיעבד b'diavad literally means after the fact, but there's
a principle of שעת הדחק כדיעבד דמי, sh'at had'chak k'b'diavad dami, like
the whole circumstance is בדיעבד, b'diavad non-ideal. Yes.
We can then extend that concept and say today on my I
can go and do eat something on יום כיפור is going to
be מכפר, m'chaper, but I'll say אחטא echta and then right, there's
always the way,
right, right, I mean, you know, there's a little bit of difference
because we're not talking about when we say ריצוי ציץ, ritzuy tzitz,
the ריצוי ציץ ritzuy tzitz is not saying it atones for the
sin, it ריצוי ציץ ritzuy tzitz means it validates the קרבן. So
that's the concern of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is whether בדיעבד
b'diavad it'll be valid or not. So there we say go ahead
and bring it בדיעבד b'diavad. it'll be valid. Now the question is,
yes, but לכתחילה lechatchila. am I not supposed am I allowed to
do that? So that, you know, and then it raises questions about
how much do you think in personal individual terms in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash or more in terms of the entire service? Like
what?
Right. Yes, but if it's a but if it's a non-fixed time
then there's no הותרה no דחויה. What's allowing the כהן to do
it? You know, then it sort of raises would we ever say
that by a personal קרבן? The general answer would be no, but
you know we sort of like at a communal level we need
this to get done. How do we focus on the individual כהן
that might be doing a violation, you know, sort of versus those
like communal, you know, בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash concerns? That seems to
be part of the issue because again if you talk about an
individual's קרבן, why didn't the גמרא Gemara, just say no we're talking
about a קרבן of a יחיד, I happened to be bringing my
my cow קרבן and the and the thing became טמא, so go
ahead and bring it anyway because ריצוי ציץ. ritzuy tzitz. No, partly
it's the communal nature which lets us say just keep on going.
So I yeah, but it's not about the sin.
And I was wondering you know about the also the the question
of תוספות Tosafot, about of these specific points of time, but I
was the way I was thinking about this in terms of you
think about it is something like עבודה זרה, avodah zarah if you're
not going to bring I understand bringing an עבודה avodah. זרה, but
you really don't want to say that. I mean here you're doing
a whole bunch of קרבנות, korbanot it's almost like טובל ושרץ בידו.
tovel v'sheretz b'yado. You've committed עבודה זרה practically, you know what I
mean? So you want to sort of like
you know okay so that so that could be the explanation of
why you say שתוק. shtoke. Okay, that could be the explanation of
why you say שתוק, shtoke, but it would not work if בדיעבד
b'diavad it wouldn't be good. That's the assumption. You wouldn't go ahead
and do it if בדיעבד bedieved it was no good.
Rabbi Zink, just the last thing, the structure the entire structure here
though, what happened to דחויה?
I know we're focusing because we're focusing on רב נחמן. We want
to see if can we make all of this evidence work with
רב נחמן. The easier read of all of the ברייתות braisos is
is that it's all a fixed time קרבן ציבור and nevertheless and
therefore if you don't have a choice go ahead and do it,
don't make an announcement about it necessarily but go ahead and do
it and if you but if you do have a choice we
prefer you to do it בטהרה. b'taharah. The simple sense of all
this is רב ששת. We're trying to make it work with רב
נחמן.
Right, so the right, so the entire structure of the סוגיא sugya
at this point is an exploration and clarification of one side of
the Exactly, exactly.
Okay, now let's keep on
going. מיתיבי. Meitivei. דם שנטמא וזרקו בשוגג. Dam shenitma v'zarko b'shogeg. Blood
became טמא and it was thrown בשוגג b'shogeg
and you they still threw it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So again
it's the thing becoming טמא, not the person. Keep that in mind
because that's then relevant for ציץ tzitz בדיעבד. bedieved If it was
בשוגג b'shogeg הורצה, hurtzah, if it was unintentional question what was unintentional,
the טומאה tumah or the throwing? That's debated in the in the
גמרא. Gemara But if it was unintentional it's valid. במזיד B'meizid if
it's intentional לא הורצה, lo hurtzah, it's non-valid. Now the simple sense
of לא הורצה lo hurtzah means the קרבן is invalid. We are
going to see in a second that that is not the הלכה,
that because of the idea of the ציץ tzitz even if it
was במזיד b'meizid and if it's the thing was טמא, the object
was טמא, even if it was brought up במזיד b'meizid בדיעבד the
קרבן will be good because of the ציץ. tzitz So the idea
במזיד לא הורצה b'meizid lo hurtzah is explained in a different גמרא
Gemara here. The simple sense is the קרבן is no good but
a different גמרא Gemara explains it to mean
that... but at least we fine the owners, the בעלים ba'alim or
the כהנים and say, you know, yes, the קרבן you were יוצא,
but don't benefit from the קרבן if it was brought if it
was טומאה tumah. and you're only getting it through because of the
because of the ציץ tzitz and you were מזיד. meizid. Okay, but
that's the issue. So the question still is again, if you're dealing
with if this were a קרבן ציבור, why should there be any
difference of בשוגג beshogeg and במזיד bemazid in any of this? If
טומאה הותרה בציבור, tumah hutra betzibur. then everything should be okay לכתחילה.
Much as that's an easy answer. כי תניא ההיא דיחיד, ki tanya
hahee d'yachid, that's a private קרבן. It has nothing to do with
טומאה הותרה בציבור. tumah hutra betzibur. Why בדיעבד is it good if
it's בשוגג? beshogeg? Because of the ציץ. tzitz Okay, תא שמע, ta
shema, come
and hear. The the the
no, no, it's like a a strip of gold, a forehead plate
that the כהן גדול would wear. It would say קודש לה' Kodesh
l'Hashem on it and it would be like it would go on
his forehead, it would be like a like a, you know, like
a one inch or two inch strip of gold. What? Not a
tiara. A tiara is a crown that has something going up. This
is like it's like a
sweatband. That's what it looks like. You look like a sweatband and
they had a string in the back, okay. What? Like the sushi
guy.
Like the sushi guy, okay. תא שמע, ta shema,
come and hear.
אמר ציץ מרצה. amar tzitz mirtzeh. Now we get to the idea
of ציץ tzitz again. ציץ tzitz, is only by the by the
when the objects become טמא, not when the people. אמר ציץ מרצה.
amar tzitz mirtzeh. What does it work for? הדם hadam and here
it spells it out. It's the blood, הבשר, habasar, the meat, החלב,
hachalev, or anything that would go on the מזבח. mizbeach. The fat,
the meat, if it were an עולה, olah, שנטמא, shenitma, became טמא,
בין בשוגג בין במזיד, bein beshogeg bein bemazid, here notice it says
בשוגג beshogeg or במזיד, bemazid, בין באונס בין ברצון, bein b'ones bein
b'ratzon, willingly, unwillingly, בין ביחיד בין בציבור, bein b'yachid bein b'tzibur, whether
personal or communal קרבן. All of this the ציץ tzitz works to
make it valid. So again, the statement before of invalid במזיד bemazid
is understood to mean that you don't eat the meat. But in
terms of the קרבן, the ציץ tzitz. works to make it valid
as long as we're talking about the objects that are being brought
up, the things, and we're not talking about the people, the ציץ
tzitz works. Now, the only problem is why did it have to
say that the ציץ tzitz. works for the ציבור? Okay, the ציבור
anyway has a free pass because
of טומאה הותרה בציבור.
hutra betzibur, אי איתמר הכי איתמר, ee itmar hachi itmar,
that's basically what we have. ואי סלקא דעתך טומאה היתר היא בציבור,
v'ee salka daitach tumah hetar hee b'tzibur, if טומאה fundamentally doesn't apply
at all the ציבור, nothing problematic happened, nothing happened, keep on moving,
nothing at all happened here. If it's a ציבור קרבן, tzibur korban,
there's not even a problem if that's your approach. למה לי לרצויי?
lama lee l'ratzuyei? Who needs the ציץ tzitz to help us out?
Absolutely nothing problematic happened. So אמר לך רב נחמן, amar lach Rav
Nachman, רב נחמן would say back to you, כי תניא הציץ מרצה
אדיחיד. ki tanya hatzitz mirtzeh ad'yachid. Fine, it throws in ציבור to
say that a קרבן ציבור will always be okay בטומאה, but the
need of the ציץ, tzitz? that wasn't for the ציבור case. The
ציץ tzitz. was for the יחיד case and yes, once it's talking
about things that are בדיעבד good בטומאה, it threw in קרבן ציבור,
but the ציבור didn't really need the ציץ. tzitz ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'is
eima, if you want I could tell you, אפילו תימא בציבור, afilu
teima b'tzibur, even by a ציבור, דהנך דלא קביע להו זמן, d'hanach
d'lo kavia lehu zman, right, that's what I thought you were going
to say, right. What? But wait! Ah, not every קרבן ציבור overrides.
What do we have? Right, the non-fixed time קרבן ציבור, the פר
עבודה זרה, par avodah zara, we can probably figure out one or
two more. So you have a קרבן ציבור without fixed time. So
that does not have the idea of טומאה הותרה בציבור. The key
about הותרה or דחויה is fixed time. So there can be a
קרבן ציבור you need the ציץ tzitz for when it is a
non-fixed time קרבן ציבור. Then you do not have the הותרה or
דחויה concept. That's when you need the ציץ. tzitz And again, that
works for when the things, the blood, the meat, etc. is טמא.
Does not work for when the people are טמא. And that's the
next line here but there was a question.
Yeah, when you have a תא שמע, ta shema, it's not followed
by a דתניא d'tanya or stuff like that, what am I looking?
You're looking at a ברייתא. braita.
Is it always looking in a ברייתא braita or a משנה Mishnah
even without?
Yeah, yeah, I yeah, תא שמע ta shema always introduces a Tannaic
source. Yeah, yeah.
What was the metaphysics that the כהן גדול patrolled the grounds always
wearing the ציץ tzitz and whatever happened?
We're going to get to that. Like what if he's not wearing
the ציץ? tzitz That's coming right up. Or he's not around? Yeah,
it's coming around. Okay, let's take a look. וכי... ve'chi... okay, now
let's take a look. מיתיבי, meitivei, I'll ask you on this. ונשא
אהרן את עון הקדשים. v'nasa Aharon es avon hakodashim. Okay, this is
what it says by wearing the ציץ. tzitz It says והיה על
מצחו תמיד, v'haya al mitzcho tamid, it will be constantly on his
forehead, ונשא אהרן את עון הקדשים, v'nasa Aharon es avon hakodashim, he
will
carry forgiveness for the sin of the of the sanctified things. וכי...
ve'chi... now again, by the way, about the idea that it's about
things and not people, right, it's about עון הקדשים, avon hakodashim, the
things that are sanctified. It's not about the people doing the עבודה.
This is about the things that are sanctified. I
also should point out, I mean, I pointed it out before but
I but I love this idea. It's so... which is... I mean,
I told you I'm reading I recently read this book that talks
about the metaphors that are used for sin and that, you know,
in the גמרא, Gemara the metaphors for sin very much have to
do with... Yet, and with God coming to collect the debt, that's
why we talk about forgiving sin as מחילה, mechilah, because you're מוחל
mochel a debt, you waive, you know, the debt and so on.
But in the תורה, the metaphor for sin being the implicit metaphor
is a burden, okay? And therefore, you can talk about, you know,
when you actually, when you actually are guilty and bear your sin,
right? It talks about ונשא עוונו venasa avono because you are carrying
the burden of your sin. But the same verb can be used
to have your sin forgiven,
because God is נושא עוון, noseh avon, God lifts your sin off
from you. So ונשא אהרן את עוון הקדשים, venasa Aharon et avon
hakodashim, he lifts off the burden of the sin and therefore makes
it forgiven and makes it acceptable.
So you're equating טומאה with sin?
Well, that's true. The פסוק pasuk says sin of the קרבנות korbanot
and it's really—that is true, it is a strange—yes, there is a
sin of bringing בטומאה, but again, the focus of the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash is more about the, you know, the problematic of the
presence of טומאה. So it is interesting.
So does טומאה equal sin?
Right. So that—yeah, that's a larger conversation about how those—also those metaphors
or those ideas get juxtaposed.
And what does sin mean in English? In other words, we might
be translating something that does not reflect the metaphorical image properly.
That could be. That could be. Okay, so let's anyway go on.
So ונשא אהרן את עוון הקדשים. venasa Aharon et avon hakodashim. וכי
איזה עוון הוא נושא? vechi eizeh avon hu noseh? No, it's a
good point why this פסוק pasuk uses עוון, avon, because normally it's
the opposite. טומאה is the more general term and that's obviously even
more appropriate here. So why it uses עוון avon is a good
question. וכי איזה עוון הוא נושא? vechi eizeh avon hu noseh? What
sin is it forgiving for, what טומאה? אם עוון פיגול הרי כבר
נאמר, im avon pigul harei kevar ne'emar, but you see, here is
exactly Rifka, because
in the פסוקים pesukim it's not clear that the ציץ tzitz is
limited to טומאה. The ציץ tzitz in the פסוקים pesukim it could
be that the ציץ tzitz makes all bad קרבנות acceptable. And there's
more than one reason a קרבן could be bad. So, you know,
so it's only חז"ל Chazal that limit or interpret, as we're about
to see, the function of the ציץ tzitz to the טומאה problem.
In the פסוקים Pesukim, it could be saying the wearing of the
ציץ tzitz makes all bad קרבנות acceptable. But that's what the גמרא
Gemara is now going to ask and it's going to limit it
to טומאה. וכי איזה עוון הוא נושא? vechi eizeh avon hu noseh?
Which sin, which bad type of קרבן does it make forgiven? Okay.
אם עוון פיגול, im avon pigul, if it is a קרבן that
is פיגול pigul which was brought with the intent to eat it
at the wrong time, הרי כבר נאמר לא ירצה. harei kevar ne'emar
lo yeratzeh. It says it shall not be made permissible. So there's
no ריצוי ritzui possible with פיגול. pigul. פיגול pigul will never be
permissible. ואם עוון נותר, ve'im avon notar, if it's the sin of
leaving over, הרי כבר נאמר לא יחשב. harei kevar ne'emar lo yechashev.
It shall not be considered. And that's actually the same פרשה parsha
of פיגול. pigul. Now there's a problem with נותר, notar, because נותר
notar happens—when does נותר notar happen? Later. Later, after the קרבן was
already good. So there's no need to make the קרבן acceptable if
there's a נותר notar problem. So there's a long רש"י Rashi תוספות
Tosafot but based on other גמרות, Gemaras, but the basic idea is
that one of these terms, either פיגול pigul or נותר, notar, refers
to the other type of thing that's like פיגול pigul that is
part of this פסוק pasuk of לא ירצה lo yeratzeh לא יחשב,
lo yechashev, which is פיגול pigul is an intention of the wrong
time, eat it at the wrong time or bring it at the
wrong time, and there's another thing of חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, an
intention to eat it in the wrong place. So פיגול pigul and
נותר notar here combined, yeah, which is which is a whole discussion
of רש"י Rashi תוספות, it doesn't really matter for us. They refer
to the two ways of invalidating with a thought of wrong time
and wrong place. And by them the פסוק pasuk says לא ירצה
lo yeratzeh לא יחשב, lo yechashev, which means no, it will never
be accepted. So the גמרא Gemara. understands that means that the ציץ
tzitz cannot work for it. הא אינו נושא—see, ha eino noseh I
bet you were concerned whether we'd finish the דף today. I knew
how big of a social sphere we'd have. הא אינו נושא אלא
עוון טומאה. ha eino noseh ella avon tumah. The only thing left
of a type of invalidity for it to make acceptable is the
invalidity of טומאה. Now, now it could have stopped there, you know,
just like okay, process of elimination. But the ברייתא Braitah goes on
to explain why it actually makes sense that of all things, טומאה
should be the one that the ציץ tzitz can work for. שהותרה
מכללה בציבור, shehutrah miklala betzibur, because we know that טומאה has other
times where it's sort of wiped away. What's times when טומאה is
not a problem? ציבור. So if we have an idea that ציץ
tzitz makes things acceptable for certain problems, so a) we know certain
problems are intractable and the ציץ tzitz can't work for. b) We
have a whole big category called טומאה which we know sometimes does
get sort of pushed aside. So it makes sense that if the
ציץ tzitz. is going to work for something, it'll work for טומאה.
And that's how we settle on the idea that the ציץ tzitz
works to make things that are טמא acceptable. Again, when the things
are טמא, not the people. Now, why is this a problem? The
only reason this is a challenge to is because it used the
word הותרה. And the גמרא Gemara understands that since the debate of
Rav Nachman and Rav Sheshet was הותרה דחויה, that technical use of
the terms is also would be present in this ברייתא Braitah as
well. Of the ברייתא braita *braita* as הותרה *hutra*, it says, oh
look, that's a support of רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*, it used the
term הותרה *hutra*. So isn't this a support of רב נחמן *Rav
Nachman*, קשיא לרב ששת *kashya l'Rav Sheshet*? So again, not because of
how the ציצית tzitzit *tzitzis* functioning, no הלכה *halacha* here challenges רב
ששת *Rav Sheshet*, the only thing that challenges רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*
is we described that the leniency of טומאה *tumah* is because of
הותרה *hutra*. We used the word הותרה *hutra*. That's a challenge for
רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says תנאי היא
*tannai hi*, it's a debate of תנאים *tannaim*. דתניא *d'tanya*, you're right.
This תנא *tanna* assumes הותרה *hutra*. רב ששת *Rav Sheshet* says believe
me, I've got תנאים *tannas* that say דחויה *dechuya*, not הותרה *hutra*.
First of all, everything we quoted on the עמוד א׳ *amud aleph*,
which really in a simple sense supports רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*. And
now he's going to quote other things. תנאי היא *tannai hi*. דתניא
*d'tanya*, it taught in a ברייתא *braita*: ציץ tzitz. *tzitz*, בין שישנו
על מצחו mitcho ובין שאינו על מצחו mitcho *bein sheyeshno al mitzcho
u'vein she'eino al mitzcho*. Right, so this is what you were saying.
Whether it's on the forehead or not on the forehead, מרצה *mirtzeh*.
It doesn't matter if he's wearing it. דברי רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
*divrei Rabbi Shimon*. That's what רב שמעון *Rav Shimon* says. רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda אומר *Rabbi Yehuda omer*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says no:
עודהו על מצחו מרצה *odeihu al mitzcho mirtzeh*, while it's on his
forehead it makes the קרבנות *korbanos* acceptable. Also you asked, the קרבן
*korban* was טמא *tamei*. Right, right. If the קרבן *korban* was brought
and it was the blood was טמא *tamei*, you'd have to say,
hey, hey Charlie, can you find out if the כהן גדול *Kohen
Gadol* was wearing his ציץ tzitz *tzitz* right at, you know, 12:06
PM?
We got a problem here. So anyway, and you'd have to go
ahead and check, was he wearing it at that moment when the
דם *dam* was put on the מזבח *mizbeach* when it was טמא
*tamei*? Was he wearing it at that moment? Okay, so עודהו על
מצחו מרצה *odeihu al mitzcho mirtzeh*, for that moment. אינו על מצחו
*eino al mitzcho*, if it wasn't on his forehead at that moment,
אינו מרצה *eino mirtzeh*. He says no. אמר לו רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon, *amar lo Rabbi Shimon*, so that has nothing to do with...
normally he would wear the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* every day.
Yeah, but let's say he wasn't... let's say he was on his
lunch break. Let's say he didn't come... come today to the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*. Okay, so so far this has nothing
to do with הותרה דחויה *hutra dechuya*, but we'll see how the
conversation continues. אמר לו רבי שמעון *amar lo Rabbi Shimon*, so רב
שמעון *Rav Shimon* said, who says he doesn't have to be wearing
it, כהן גדול ביום הכפורים יוכיח *Kohen Gadol b'Yom HaKippurim yochiach*. I've
got a day that I know there's the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*
is not wearing the ציץ tzitz *tzitz*. What's that day? יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur*. Because on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*,
he's leaving it outside.
Okay, but there's times he's not wearing it. Right. Let's say the
קרבן *korban* becomes טמא *tamei* at that time. So the כהן גדול
*Kohen Gadol* is not wearing the ציץ tzitz, *tzitz* at certain times,
right, when he is doing the עבודה *avodah* in the inside, in
the... in the... in the היכל *Heichal*, right, not the עבודה *avodah*
out in the outer מזבח *mizbeach*, but all the stuff he does
on the inside. He's only wearing the white garments, not the ציץ
tzitz *tzitz*. And what if the קרבן *korban* became טמא *tamei*? We
know it would still be good. So you see that the... well,
we have that acceptable and that's what מסכת יומא *Masechet Yoma* is
about. So you see that the ציץ tzitz, *tzitz* still functions even
when he's not wearing it. Let's just finish. שאינו על מצחו *she'eino
al mitzcho*, it's not on his forehead then, ומרצה *u'mirtzeh*. We know
that בדיעבד *b'di'eved* if things became טמא *tamei* at that time, בדיעבד
*b'di'eved* it would still be good.
The קרבן *korban* that he...
the קרבן *korban* that he is doing in the, you know, in
the inner sanctum there, if it became טמא בדיעבד *tamei b'di'eved* it
would be good even though he's not wearing the ציץ tzitz *tzitz*.
So you see it's מרצה *mirtzeh*. No one else is doing it.
Exactly. אמר לו רבי יהודה *amar lo Rabbi Yehuda*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* says: הנח לכהן גדול ביום הכפורים שטומאה הותרה לו בציבור *hanach
l'Kohen Gadol b'Yom HaKippurim she'tumah hutra lo b'tzibbur*. One minute. Fine. That
has nothing to do with the ציץ *tzitz*. It's a כהן גדול
*Kohen Gadol* on יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*. It's הותרה בציבור *hutra b'tzibbur*. Now again, we said technically it's
not necessarily ציבור *tzibbur*, could be his personal קרבן *korban*, but again
it means a קרבן *korban* that has a fixed time. Just who
needs to talk about ציץ *tzitz* there? It's a fixed time קרבן
*korban*, it's his קרבן *korban* or the ציבור's *tzibbur's* קרבן *korban*. Of
course טומאה *tumah* will be בדיעבד *b'di'eved* at least בדיעבד *b'di'eved* be
okay or even לכתחילה הותרה בציבור *l'chatchila hutra b'tzibbur*. So you can't
prove me that it's about the functioning of the ציץ *tzitz*. It's
about the fact that it's a כהן גדול's *Kohen Gadol's* קרבן *korban*
on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מכלל
*micklal*, so if that's what how רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* answers back,
that's an excellent point. What the heck was רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*
thinking? How did רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* think that the ציץ *tzitz*
has any role in a כהן גדול's *Kohen Gadol's* קרבן *korban* on
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*? מכלל דרבי שמעון סבר טומאה דחויה היא בציבור
*micklal d'Rabbi Shimon savar tumah dechuya hi b'tzibbur*. So if the ציץ
*tzitz* needs to be doing something, if it was הותרה *hutra* it
wouldn't need to be doing anything. But if it but if it's
only דחויה *dechuya*, then maybe the ציץ *tzitz* can come and also
do a function. Now exactly how those two work together is not
clear because at the end of the day until this moment we
basically said that if דחויה *dechuya* only means if you've got another
choice go for it. You don't have another choice here. You've got
the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*, you've got the one קרבן *korban*, you
don't have another choice. So you know, רב ששת *Rav Sheshet* who
says דחויה *dechuya* would say go ahead and do it. You don't
have another choice, טומאה דחויה בציבור *tumah dechuya b'tzibbur* go ahead and
do it. And that means that it's good. It's a good קרבן
*korban*. So exactly what the ציץ *tzitz* does in addition is not
clear. Who, you know, even with דחויה *dechuya*, who needs the ציץ
*tzitz*? Okay, so תוספות *Tosafot*, that's why some of these big תוספות
*Tosafot* in מסכתא *Masechta* are trying to figure that out. But at
least at some conceptual level the גמרא *Gemara* says: Yes, you're allowed
to do it. Yes, you're יוצא *yotzei*, but it's sort of a
בדיעבד יוצא *b'di'eved yotzei*. So the ציץ *tzitz* doesn't hurt to have
the ציץ *tzitz* if your concept is a דחויה *dechuya* concept. Okay,
so basically what do we have at this stage? Let me just
refresh us. On the עמוד א׳ *amud aleph* we quoted a list
of ברייתות *braitot* that basically say that in the simplest sense you're
bringing a קרבן ציבור *korban tzibbur* and it became טמא *tamei*, better
to get a טהור *tahor* one. And if not, then בדיעבד *b'di'eved*
it's okay. That seems to be a perfect scenario description of דחויה
בציבור *dechuya b'tzibbur*. קרבן ציבור *korban tzibor*. בדיעבד *bedieved* it'll be okay,
but better to get a טהור *tahor* one. The basic answer if
you say הותרה *hutra* was to say those in one way or
another weren't really קרבן ציבור *korban tzibors*. Okay, and therefore, or special
cases, either you wanted to eat the שיריים *shirayim*, or it was
only an individual even if it's time or maybe it wasn't even
something that would override טומאה *tumah* at all. It was a this
פר *par*... this bull of עבודה זרה *avoda zara*, but בדיעבד *bedieved*
all those things will be okay because of the ציץ *tzitz*. Okay,
that's how he got out of that it was not about its
being a ציבור *tzibur*. Now we turn to the issue of the...
of the ציץ *tzitz* and we say we have a ברייתא *braita*
that in describing the ציץ *tzitz* and describing why the ציץ *tzitz*
functions for טומאה *tumah*, points out that the weakness of טומאה *tumah*
is הותרה *hutra*. Okay, and that seems to use the term הותרה
*hutra* as a proof on that side. The response back is, it's
actually a debate and according to this whole discussion would you have
needed the ציץ *tzitz* to help you out if the קרבן *korban*
became טמא *tamei* with the כהן גדול *kohen gadol* on יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur* is this question of הותרה *hutra* or דחויה *dechuya*. Okay,
and if you say the ציץ *tzitz* has no function there you
hold הותרה *hutra*, and if you say the ציץ *tzitz* does have
a function there it's because in principle you hold דחויה *dechuya* and
therefore even though בדיעבד *bedieved* it would be okay, it's always good
to have the ציץ *tzitz* to help out as well because דחויה
*dechuya* acknowledges that there was something problematic going on here. Okay, question,
Seth, you have your hand up? Yeah.
Is there any way you could explain what is like the metaphysical
principle
behind the ציץ *tzitz*?
The ציץ *tzitz*? No, I cannot. Actually I know, but I'm not
allowed to tell you.
You know, it's much better when you go to the גמרא *Gemara*
because the גמרא *Gemara* just worries about like the mechanics, halakhically does
it work in this case, work in that case, whatever. But you
know, obviously yes, the תורה *Torah* speaks in much more metaphysical terms,
like somehow the fact that he has קודש להשם *kodesh lashem*, you
know, somehow does something to the fact that these קרבנות *korbanot* were...
but I don't have a good answer to that. Okay, did you
have a question? No? Okay, very quickly.
How do all these problems come up? After all, don't they have
checks and balances from the moment it's bought?
They do, but טומאה *tumah* is something like I said, like as
Michael said, an animal could be slaughtered incorrectly, you know, you can't
control nature, right? An animal could crawl into the בית המקדש *Beis
Hamikdash* as a שרץ *sheretz*.
Yeah, so טומאה *tumah* would happen. Right, but it leads back
to דחויה *dechuya* vs הותרה *hutra*.
Yeah.
How does אהרן *Aaron*'s ram
fit into this in the end?
So אהרן *Aaron*'s ram, even though it's יחיד *yachid*, overrides טומאה *tumah*
or allows is allowed to be done בטומאה *be'tumah* because it has
a fixed time and the question is, okay, but when it was
done with טומאה *tumah* was it still seen as somewhat problematic? That
depends on the הותרה *hutra*/דחויה *dechuya* debate. Okay, and that depends on
whether the ציץ *tzitz* has any place to be functioning. What? He's
not wearing it. So either that's an evidence that... either that's an
evidence that the ציץ *tzitz* works when he's not wearing it, or
there's two ways to explain how does that... either the ציץ *tzitz*
works when he's not wearing it, or no, you need the ציץ
*tzitz* only works when it's being worn, but you don't need the
ציץ *tzitz* because of הותרה *hutra*. Okay, exactly. You've got... no? Okay,
so let's finish the דף *daf*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like
this. Okay, so now we're going to have the... now we're going
to
shift... so that laid out the two camps and dealt with various
evidence on both sides. And now we're going to shift this discussion
to when the ציץ *tzitz* operates, does he have to be wearing
it? Again, when the objects are טמא *tamei*, not the people. People
only works when it's a case of הותרה *hutra* or דחויה בציבור
*dechuya b'tzibur*, but the ציץ *tzitz* works on the objects. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this, אמר אביי Abaye *amar Abaye*. So אביי
Abaye *Abaye* is going to come and relate to this debate. We're
moving on. ונשבר הציץ דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דלא מרצה *venishbar hatzitz
dechulei alma lo peligi delo meratzeh*. If the ציץ *tzitz* is broken,
okay, it doesn't like exist, then everybody agrees it's not functioning and
the presence of the ציץ *tzitz* does not make the קרבנות *korbanot*
acceptable. כי פליגי דתלוי בכוכפתא *ki peligi detalui bekuchta*. The debate is
that the ציץ *tzitz* is hanging on its peg, it's in the
כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*'s locker, okay, he's not wearing it, it's in
his locker, but the ציץ *tzitz* exists. Okay. רבי יהודה סבר *Rabbi
Yehuda savar*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* who says that he has to
be wearing the ציץ *tzitz* in order for it to function, על
מצח Metzach, *al metzach*, it says, the ציץ *tzitz* should be on
the forehead of אהרן *Aaron*, ונשא venasa, אהרן את עון הקדשים *venasa
Aharon et avon hakodashim*, he will lift off the sin of the
sacrifices. So על מצח ונשא *al metzach venasa*. So he reads those
words juxtaposed as they are. When it's on his forehead, that's when
it lifts off the sin. רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, רבי שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon* says he doesn't have to be wearing it, סבר *savar*, תמיד
tamid לרצון leratzon, לפני השם *tamid leratzon lifnei Hashem*. So he does
a very cute... he does a very cute read, right? It says
והיה על מצח אהרן תמיד tamid *vehaya al metzach Aharon tamid*, I
believe is the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*... והיה *vehaya*... Michael, you have the
פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*? Could you read it?
והיה על מצח אהרן ונשא אהרן את עון הקדשים אשר יקדישו בני
ישראל לכל מתנת קדשיהם והיה על מצחו תמיד Tamid לרצון להם לפני
השם *Vehaya al metzach Aharon venasa Aharon et avon hakodashim asher yakdishu
bnei Yisrael lechol matnot kodsheihem vehaya al mitcho tamid leratzon lahem lifnei
Hashem*.
Okay, so one פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* says על מצח ונשא *al metzach
venasa* is juxtaposed at the beginning of the פסוק *pasuk*, on the
forehead and ונשא *venasa*, and at the end it says, right, והיה
על מצחו תמיד לרצון להם *vehaya al mitcho tamid leratzon lahem*. Now
of course even that sounds like when it's on his forehead then
it is לרצון להם *leratzon lahem*, but רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* conveniently
cuts out the word forehead that precedes it. And says תמיד לרצון
להם. It'll always be לרצון, even if he's not wearing it, תמיד
לרצון לפני ה׳. tamid leratzon lifnei Hashem. So מאי תמיד? mai tamid?
אילימא תמיד על מצחו, ilima tamid al mitcho, if it's like the
פסוק sounds, it's constantly on his forehead and only then is it
atoning, מי משכחת לה, mi mishkachat lah, who can wear who can
wear it on your forehead all the time? מי לא בעי מיעל
לבית הכיסא, mi lo baei meial leveit hakise, doesn't he ever have
to go to the bathroom?
Okay. So I mean you could sleep with your ציץ on, but
no but you have human functions that you're not allowed to do
with your ציץ on. ומי לא בעי מינם? umi lo baei minam?
Doesn't he have to sleep? And again, the idea because we learned
there's a whole comparison which we're about to deal with about ציץ
and תפילין tefillin and the idea now תפילין tefillin you're not allowed
to sleep, one reason is because of passing gas, but there's another
idea which we focus the comparison of ציץ and תפילין tefillin about
the idea of תמיד לפני ה׳ tamid lifnei Hashem and this maybe
begins to answer your point, Seth, about constant consciousness of God. You
know we sort of we say God should always be in the
forefront of your thoughts, you know sort of like on your forehead.
So the idea you're sleeping, that's not a time to be wearing
the ציץ. The ציץ is about being conscious of God on your
forehead, God's name on your forehead. So he can't always be wearing
it. So what does תמיד mean? אלא תמיד לרצון הוא. ela tamid
leratzon hu. It always always makes the קרבן acceptable even if he's
not wearing it. So now the גמרא says, okay, what do they
what do you do with each other's פסוק? ורבי יהודה נמי הא
כתיב תמיד? veRebbi Yehuda nami ha ktiv tamid? What does he do
with the תמיד? Because again it can't literally mean he's wearing it
all the time. ההוא תמיד שלא יסיח דעתו ממנו. hahu tamid shelo
yassiach da'ato mimeno. It means constantly conscious of it when you're wearing
it. Not wear it all the time, but when you're wearing it
you should be constantly aware of it. It should
create a constant consciousness. כי דרבה בר רב הונא דאמר רבה בר
רב הונא, ki deRabba bar Rav Huna de'amar Rabba bar Rav Huna,
that's exactly what I'm saying to you. חייב אדם למשמש בתפילין בכל
שעה ושעה. chayav adam lemashesh bitefillin bechol sha'ah vesha'ah. You have to
be when you're wearing תפילין tefillin touching them constantly, meaning always sort
of you know sort of like invoking your awareness of them.
קל וחומר מציץ. kal vachomer mitzitz. And you learn it from the
ציץ. Now why is it a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? You would
think the ציץ demands much more than the תפילין. tefillin. Here's the
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה ציץ שאין בו אלא אזכרה אחת אמרה
תורה על מצחו תמיד. u'mah tzitz she'ein bo ela azkarah achat amrah
Torah al mitcho tamid. The ציץ that only has one name of
God says קודש לה׳ kodesh l'Hashem on your forehead constantly and constantly
understood to mean constant consciousness of
it, שלא יסיח דעתו ממנו. shelo yassiach da'ato mimeno. תפילין שיש בהן
אזכרות הרבה על אחת כמה וכמה, tefillin sheyesh bahen azkarot harbeh al
achat kamah vechamah, how much more so. Now תוספות says this is
obviously not a real קל וחומר. kal vachomer. First of all the
תפילין׳ס tefillin's names of God are hidden in the box and the
ציץ׳ס tzitz's names of God are on the ציץ and exposed to
all and so that name of God and that obviously can demand
different things. It's also the בגד beged of a כהן גדול could
demand different things. But nevertheless that's the idea and the גמרא does
have a whole comparison. It's interesting the analogies of the תפילין, tefillin,
particularly של ראש shel rosh to the ציץ, also seems to be
analogies by the way about ציצית tzitzit to the בגדים begadim of
the כהן גדול. So this whole idea about you know we in
the larger world we no longer have a בית המקדש and we're
not כהנים, most of us, but this sense of sort of bringing
that קדושה kedushah with us in our activities and thinking about the
תפילין tefillin as a ציץ and the ציצית tzitzit as a and
the תפילין tefillin and ציצית tzitzit sort of go together, but okay,
and the ציצית as a type of בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah is
an important metaphor in the or images in the גמרא. So as
basic and in terms of us, the technical point is, how doesn't
it say תמיד? So תמיד shouldn't תמיד mean it constantly atones? And
no, תמיד doesn't mean constant atoning, it means when it's worn, constant
consciousness. And now let's just end with what רבי שמעון does with
the other פסוק. ולרבי שמעון דאמר תמיד מרצה, u'leRebbi Shimon de'amar tamid
mertze, that it's always atone is the wrong word, always makes the
קרבן acceptable והא כתיב על מצחו ונשא? ve'ha ktiv al mitcho venasa?
What about the juxtaposition of forehead and lifts off lifts off the
sin? So it seemingly only when it's on his forehead it functions.
So the גמרא says ההוא לקבוע לו מקום הוא דאתא. hahu likvoa
lo makom hu de'ata. That's just to tell you, forget ונשא, it's
to tell you where you put the ציץ, on his forehead. So
רבי יהודה לקבוע לו מקום מנא ליה? so Rebbi Yehuda likvoa lo
makom mena leh? So where does רבי יהודה know know that idea
that it's on his forehead? נפקא ליה מעל מצחו. nafka leh me'al
mitcho. Because it says forehead. He says, I'm not saying my point
from forehead, I'm saying my point from the juxtaposition of forehead with
atoning. רבי שמעון נמי תיפוק ליה מעל מצחו. Rebbi Shimon nami tipok
leh me'al mitcho. The very fact it says forehead tells you forehead.
Our point here is not the words מצחו but its juxtaposition. אין
הכי נמי. in hachi nami.
You're right, you're right, you're right. מצחו that tells you forehead. אלא
על מצחו ונשא מאי עביד ליה? ela al mitcho venasa mai avid
leh? What do you do about the juxtaposition that seems to say
only when it's on the forehead does it function? מה עביד ליה?
mai avid leh? What does he do with it? אמר לך
ראוי למצח מרצה שאין ראוי למצח אינו מרצה. amar lach ra'ui lemach
mirtze she'ein ra'ui lemach eino mirtze. Only when it's fit to be
on his forehead can it work does it function. Not when it's
not fit. לאפוקי נשבר הציץ דלא מרצה, la'apukei nishbar hatzitz dela mirtze,
to exclude the time when it's
broken, he can't put it on his forehead, then it doesn't work.
So at the end of the day this sort of is the
way אביי frames the debate that it's a debate does it work
constantly every I mean the גמרא says, the ברייתא says, is it
does the ציץ work constantly or only when it's being worn? אביי
says they would agree when it's not fit to be worn, and
then the גמרא elaborates that they're learning it out from different parts
of the פסוקים, either the one that focuses on תמיד or the
one that focuses on מצח, but what do you do with the
simple sense that he has to be wearing it? Says רבי שמעון,
it just means it has to be fit to be worn. But
according to him, even if it's not being worn, it still functions.
And that, and that again
is what allows קרבנות even when you do not have the הותרה
בציבור, דחויה בציבור when the קרבן is טמא, allows them to be
acceptable.